<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<title>Introduction</title>

<introduction>
<p>The subject we are about to study, Linear Algebra, sounds like it might have something to do with lines and doing algebra with them.  This is true if you are willing to think metaphorically<ellipsis /> It might be somewhat closer to the truth if we were to say that Linear Algebra is about learning to understand higher dimensions.  We'll be surprisingly far along in our study of the topic before we can precisely define what <q>dimension</q> actually means, but we expect that you have some notion already: the Euclidean plane where we studied Geometry is two dimensional, the world we live in is three dimensional, Albert Einstein taught us to view the world not just as space <mdash /> but as space-time <mdash /> a four dimensional concept.  We needn't jump off into super advanced physics (or science fiction for that matter) in order to understand higher dimensionality.  Dimension, at least informally, just means the number of real numbers it takes to describe something. Locating a point in three-dimensional space requires three numbers <mdash /> usually <m>x</m>, <m>y</m> and <m>z</m>.  If we are keeping track of aircraft, knowing where they are in 3-space is certainly necessary, but it might also be a good idea to keep abreast of <em>which way they are going</em>!  To truly understand an aircraft's state, one needs to have six numbers: <m>x</m>, <m>y</m> and <m>z</m>, but also the velocity components <m>x'</m>, <m>y'</m> and <m>z'</m>.  This make the state of an airplane 6-dimensional.  Perhaps this is why air traffic controllers make the big bucks.</p>

<p>The 6-dimensionality of an aircraft's state may seem somewhat artificial.  Aren't we really just dealing with two separate 3-dimensional entities?</p>

<p>In Economics there is a high-dimensional entity known as the Leontief Input-Output model.  In
this model the state of an Economic system is described by a large number of real quantities, one for each sector of the economy.  In a 1965 Scientific American article Wassily Leontief (who won a Nobel prize for this work) described his model in terms of a <q>toy example</q> where the economy was divided into 82 sectors.  Today one could easily develop a Leontief I/O model where the economy was divided up into a million sectors.  Perhaps this is why Economsts make even bigger bucks.</p>

<p>When we do Linear Algebra in two dimensions we are indeed talking about lines.  One of the classic problems is to figure out whether two lines intersect and if so, where.  This is a situation where our ability to visualize things in two dimensions can lead us straight to the answer.  That is certainly not the case in a million (or even in six) dimensions.  Fortunately, there are calculational techniques that work (and even work fairly quickly on a good computer) in
just about any number of dimensions you may be interested in.</p>

<p>There are three different ways of looking at linear algebra problems: systems of linear equations, vector equations, and transformations.  These three views actually represent the same underlying structure, just in different ways.  There are various situations where one of these three viewpoints is preferable, so it is a good idea to be able to switch back and forth between these representations.</p>
</introduction>

<section>
<title>Getting started</title>
<p>The first problem we're going to look at is fairly trivial.  I bet you can solve this in your head:</p>

<blockquote><p>I'm thinking of two numbers <m>x</m> and <m>y</m>.  Their sum is 42, and their difference is 6.  What are they?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This word problem can be instantly translated into a pair of equations.  Later, when we have more sophisticated problems there may be many more unknown quantities and there may be many more equations.  Here we are dealing with a system of equations having 2 equations in 2 unknowns.

<md>
  <mrow>x+y=42</mrow>
  <mrow>x-y=6</mrow>
</md>
</p>

<p>This one is about as easy as a system of two equations in two variables can get.  Actually, that's not quite true. The easiest form for a system of two equations in two unknowns is if they basically just are statements of the answer, like:
<md>
  <mrow>x = 24</mrow>
  <mrow>y = 18.</mrow>
</md>
</p>

<p>Solving a system of equations just means (somehow) transforming it from something like the first form to something like this latter form. There are a small number of simple procedures that we can apply to systems without effecting their solutions. We can use these operations to convert almost any system into one that looks like that latter form (each equation just states what the value of some variable is). We'll get around to the full story in section 1.2, but for now, notice that if we add the two original equations together (adding equations means adding left sides and adding right sides separately) we get something that only involves <m>x</m>. And of course, once we know one of the variables it isn't very hard to find the other.
</p>

<p>We glossed-over a small but important issue in the above. How do we know that our answer was the only answer? And for that matter, is it necessarily true that there must be an answer to some system of equations? These are what are known as existance and uniqueness questions: Does there exist an answer to our problem? (Existance.) And, if there is an answer, how do we know it is the only answer? (Uniqueness.) There are systems of equations where all of the possible behaviors are exhibited: no solutions, unique solutions and lots of solutions.
</p>

<exercise>
  <statement>
    <p>Explain why the following system has no solutions at all.
    <md>
      <mrow>2x - y = 7</mrow>
      <mrow>2y - 4x = 8.</mrow>
    </md>
    </p>
  </statement>
  <hint>
    <p>Put both equations into slope-intercept form (<m>y = mx + b</m>).</p>
  </hint>
</exercise>

<p>
  That was a linear algebra problem seen from the <q>systems of equations</q> perspective. We still need to look at the <q>vector equations</q> and <q>transformations</q> viewpoints. So next we'll look at a question of the vector flavor. We're going to think about playing chess, not on a board, but on the infinite <m>x</m><mdash /><m>y</m> plane.
</p>
<p>
  Consider the piece known as a bishop. If you're not familiar with chess, this is the piece that can move in the diagonal directions. Think of the bishop as having two moves that it can do (but it can do them any number of times). It can do a move we'll refer to as UR; move one unit in the <m>x</m> direction while simultaneously moving one unit in the <m>y</m> direction <mdash /> by doing this multiple times the bishop can travel in the upper right direction. It also has a move that allows it to travel along the other diagonal <mdash /> move one unit in the <m>x</m> direction while simultaneously moving negative one unit in the <m>y</m> direction. We'll call that move LR.
</p>
<p>For those who are familiar with chess, you'll know that bishops are forever trapped on the same color square <mdash /> one of your bishops is always on black and the other always on white. This means that some <q>bishop moving questions</q> won't have solutions <mdash /> for example a bishop sitting at the origin, <m>(0, 0)</m>, can never move to <m>(0, 5)</m>; those squares have opposite colors! To get around this limitation we're going to let our bishops make fractional moves. For instance if it starts at the origin and makes <m>1/2</m> of the upper-right move then it will arrive at <m>(1/2, 1/2)</m>.  Now, getting a little stranger, we're going to also allow our bishops to make negative moves. Maybe we should think of a negative move as <q>undoing</q> a regular move<ellipsis />
</p>


<p>In any case negative moves allow us to move the bishop in the opposite directions along the diagonals.  Finally, we may as well give our bishops the freedom to move <em>any amount</em> <mdash /> that is, any real number can be used as a so-called scalar, shrinking or stretching either of the two basic moves. Got it?
We can do things like <m>\pi \cdot UR</m> and <m>\sqrt{2} \cdot LR</m>.
</p>

<p>So, after all that setup, here's the question: If a bishop starts at <m>(0,0)</m>, can it make some number of UR and LR moves and wind up at <m>(42,6)</m>?  If so, how many URs and how many LRs?
</p>

</section>

<section>
<title>Systems of equations</title>
<p>Dummy text for introduction.</p>
</section>

<section>
<title>Vector equations</title>
<p>Dummy text for introduction.</p>
</section>

<section>
<title>Transformations</title>
<p>Dummy text for introduction.</p>
</section>

<section>
<title>Matrix notation</title>
<p>Dummy text for introduction.</p>
</section>

</chapter>
